(peaceful uplifting music)
（平和振奋的音乐）
(train rattling)
(火车咔嗒咔嗒声)
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
- Do you think they'll have changed?
- 你觉得他们会改变吗？
- Oh, Mother, surely not in three months.
- 哦，妈妈，三个月后肯定不行。
- My dear when you were there age--
- 亲爱的，当你在那儿的时候——
- Yes I know.
- 是的，我知道。
And they were dragged off to the city
他们被拖到了城里
by some stranger as well.
还有一些陌生人。
- The place has been so quiet without them.
- 这个地方已经 没有他们，这里很安静。
- Yes it has rather.
- 是的，确实如此。
(train horn whistles)
（火车汽笛声）
(train rattling)
(火车咔嗒咔嗒声)
- Lucien Voiceover It was your fault.
- [吕西安画外音]都是你的错。
It was all your fault.
都是你的错。
- There's papa!
- 爸爸在那儿！
(laughing)
(笑着说)
- Lucien Voiceover Do you know what you've done?
- [吕西安画外音]Do 你知道你做了什么吗？
Done, done, done, done.
完了，完了，完了，完了。
- You did it on purpose didn't you?
- 你是故意的，是吗？
You pushed me.
是你逼我的。
- You shouldn't have got in the way then.
- 那你就不该碍事。
- I didn't!
- 我没有！
You ran right into me
你正好撞到我了
and knocked all my books on to the ground.
把我所有的书都打翻在地。
- I did not.
- 我没有。
- Yes you did, I saw you.
- 是的，我看到了。
- You liar.
- 你这个骗子。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wood tapping)
(木攻丝)
- Get off.
- 走开。
Get off!
走开!
- Who are these for?
- 这些是给谁的？
- They're for Annette.
- 是给安妮特的。
No don't!
不不!
No, get off!
不，走开！
Please give them back to me, those are for Annette.
请把它们还给 我，这些是给安妮特的。
Oh don't, please.
哦，别这样。
- Well I think your sister's stupid.
- 我觉得你妹妹很蠢。
- Oh.
——哦。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
I'm going to tell my daddy on you.
我要向我爸爸告状。
(cat screeches)
(猫捡球)
- What are you going to do?
- 你要做什么？
- Give me my kitten back!
把我的小猫还给我！
(laughs)
(笑)
Klaus.
克劳斯。
(groaning)
(呻吟)
(cat meows)
(喵喵叫的猫)
Klaus.
克劳斯。
Dani, what are you doing?
达尼，你在干什么？
Dani!
达尼！
- Klaus!
——克劳斯!
- Dani let me get him.
- 达尼，我来接他。
Dani come back.
达尼，回来。
Dani.
达尼。
(screaming)
(尖叫)
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
Dani!
丹尼!
Dani.
达尼。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
- Grandma Burnier Hello Annette.
- [奶奶Burnier]你好Annette。
- Hello.
-  -  -  -  -  - 你好。
- What have you been doing?
- 你最近在做什么？
- Oh, not very much really.
- 哦，不太喜欢。
We were helping papa,
我们在帮爸爸，
and then I came back to get the lunch ready.
然后我就回来了 去准备午餐。
- Isn't Dani with you?
-  Dani没和你在一起吗？
- No, I left him with papa.
- 不，我把他留给爸爸了。
They should be back soon.
他们应该很快就回来了。
I'm glad you came to stay with us.
我很高兴你来和我们住在一起。
It was my idea.
这是我的主意。
- I'm afraid I'm getting a bit old to be of much use,
- 恐怕我要 有点老了，没什么用了，
I'll do what I can.
我会尽我所能。
- Papa was going to have to sell some of the cows
- 爸爸本来要吃 去卖一些牛
to pay for a housekeeper, seems so awful.
花钱请个管家，看起来太可怕了。
- I was delighted to come.
- 我很高兴能来。
You seem to have managed splendidly.
你似乎处理得很好。
You've become quite the little mother haven't you?
你变得相当 小妈妈，不是吗？
- Working hard I see.
- 努力工作，我明白了。
- Where's Dani?
-  Dani在哪里？
- Isn't he here?
- 他不在这儿吗？
- I left him with you.
- 我把他留给你了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Dani!
——丹尼!
C'mon Annette.
来吧安妮特。
Dani!
丹尼!
- I wonder if Lucien knows where he is.
- 不知道吕西安知不知道他在哪儿。
He was there when I left.
我离开的时候他还在。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
Oh Madam Morell, please my I speak to Lucien?
哦，莫雷尔夫人，请 我能和吕西安说话吗？
- Yes if you can find him, wretched boy.
- 是的，如果你能找到他，可怜的孩子。
All he's got to do is milk the cow for me.
他所要做的就是帮我挤牛奶。
- But, please, when he comes--
- 但是，拜托，当他来的时候——
- Not good enough, I've got far too much to do as it is.
- 不够好，我有 现在要做的事情太多了。
- When he comes will you ask him if he's seen Dani.
- 他什么时候来，你会 问他有没有看到Dani。
He disappeared more than an hour ago
他一个多小时前失踪了
and we haven't seen him since.
从那以后我们就再没见过他。
- Where did you last see him?
- 你最后一次见到他是在哪里？
- Up by the top woods.
- 在树林的顶端。
Lucien was there at the time
吕西安当时就在那里
and I thought they might have gone off together.
我想他们会的 一起走了。
- Oh dear.
- 哦，天哪。
(Lucien sobs)
（吕西安抽泣）
- What was that?
- 那是什么？
It's them.
这是他们。
(footsteps clattering)
(脚步卡嗒卡嗒响)
- Lucien, what's the matter?
-  Lucien，怎么了？
Are you all right?
你还好吗？
- Dani.
——达尼。
Where is he?
他在哪里？
What have you done with him?
你对他做了什么？
Tell me. you've got to tell me!
告诉我。你一定要告诉我！
- It wasn't my fault!
- 那不是我的错！
- What wasn't your fault?
- 什么不是你的错？
- Lucien. - Where is he?
——吕西安。 - 他在哪里？
- You do know!
- 你知道的！
- Quiet. - You're lying!
——安静。 - 你在撒谎！
- Madam he's got to tell me. - Do you know where Dani is?
- 夫人，他得告诉我。 - 你知道达尼在哪吗？
Do you know where Dani is?
你知道达尼在哪里吗？
- He's dead.
- 他死了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Where?
——在哪里?
- Where is he?
- 他在哪儿？
Move.
移动。
- I'm going to kill you.
- 我要杀了你。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(clock ticking)
(时钟的滴答声)
- Oh Lord, no.
- 天啊，不。
- He's, down there.
- 他在下面。
- Huh?
——嗯?
- Keep away from the edge.
- 远离边缘。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Be careful.
- 小心点。
- The kitten's here.
- 小猫来了。
There you go.
好了。
- Got him.
- 抓到他了。
- Monsieur Burnier Can you see him?
-  [mr Burnier]你能看到他吗？
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Annette Be careful.
- [安妮特]小心点。
- It's all right Dani, I'm coming.
- 没事的，达尼，我来了
Dani?
达尼？
Dani.
达尼。
Oh.
哦。
- Is he alive?
- 他会没事吗？
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(clock ticking)
(时钟的滴答声)
- He shall give his angels charge over thee.
- 他应该给予他的 天使为你而战。
- Is he going to be all right?
- 他会没事吗？
- Yes, I'm sure he will.
- 是的，我相信他会的。
Let's get him back to the house.
我们把他带回家吧。
Just take his ankles, very gently.
轻轻地抓住他的脚踝。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- They ought to be at the hospital by now,
- 他们现在应该在医院了
poor little thing.
可怜的小东西。
- Grandma, what shall we do with Lucien Morell?
- 奶奶，我们该怎么办 吕西安·莫雷尔怎么办？
He should be punished.
他应该受到惩罚。
But I can't think of anything to pay him back.
但是我想不起来 只要能报答他。
- Have you ever thought Annette that when we do wrong
- 你有没有想过 安妮特，当我们做错事的时候
it often brings it's own punishment
它常常招致自己的惩罚
without anyone else interfering.
没有其他人的干涉。
Think of how afraid Lucien must have been
想想吕西安当时有多害怕吧
when he saw Dani fall.
当他看到Dani倒下时。
And how miserable he must be feeling tonight.
他是多么可怜啊 今晚一定感觉很好。
Think of how afraid he must be
想想他该有多害怕
of people finding out what he's done,
害怕人们发现他的所作所为
and what they're going to say.
以及他们会说什么。
And then think perhaps
然后想想也许
whether he hasn't been punished quite enough.
他是否还没有 惩罚够了。
And whether we could forgive him
以及我们是否能原谅他
and help him to start again.
并帮助他重新开始。
(door knocking)
(门敲门)
- Annette, what on earth's going on?
- 安妮特，这到底是怎么回事？
I can't get anything out of them at home.
在家里我什么也问不出来。
- Dani's broken his leg and it's all your brother's fault.
- 丹尼摔断了腿 都是你哥哥的错。
- What?
——什么?
- Lucien dropped the kitten into the ravine
-  Lucien掉了 小猫掉进了峡谷
and then Dani fell in after it.
然后丹尼也掉进去了
In fact it wouldn't surprise me if he pushed him.
事实上，这并不奇怪 我，如果他推了他。
- Annette, he couldn't--
- 安妮特他不能——
- He was down there on the rocks for hours
- 他在下面的岩石上呆了好几个小时
and Lucien never even told anyone.
吕西安甚至没告诉过任何人。
He could have been dead by now.
他现在可能已经死了。
- Marie.
——玛丽。
Annette.
安妮特。
I feel awful about Dani as well
我也为Dani感到难过
but all I can do for him now, is to pray for him.
但我能为他做的 现在，我只能为他祈祷。
If I allowed myself to feel as you do, and I could,
如果我允许自己去感受 如果我能像你一样，
then I wouldn't even be able to pray for him.
那我甚至都不会 可以为他祈祷
God is love.
上帝就是爱。
I can't go to him full of hatred
我不能带着仇恨去找他
and expect him to listen to me.
希望他听我的。
Leave Lucien to God, he rewards both good and evil.
把吕西安交给上帝吧，他 善恶兼得。
And remember, he loves Lucien,
记住，他爱吕西安
every bit as much as he loves Dani.
就像他爱Dani一样
- He couldn't possibly.
- 他不可能。
- I'm afraid he does.
- 恐怕他有。
- Well in that case, I shall leave the praying to you.
- 好吧，既然这样，我会的 让你去祈祷吧。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- He disgusts me.
- 他让我恶心。
Will you be all right?
你会没事吧？
I must get down to the hotel, I'm late already.
我得下去了 我已经晚了。
I'll get back as early as I can tonight.
今晚我会尽快赶回来的。
- I simply can't understand why you didn't call anyone.
- 我就是不明白 你为什么不给任何人打电话。
(sighs)
(叹息)
If that Burnier child is badly injured, we shall be ruined.
如果那个Burnier的孩子很糟糕 受了伤，我们就完了。
We'll have to pay all the bills
我们得付所有的账单
and we can't possibly afford it.
而且我们不可能负担得起。
Oh Lucien, how could you do such a thing?
哦，吕西安，你怎么能这么做？
Don't you want any?
你不想要吗？
Then get ready for school.
然后准备去上学。
Don't let the other children bother you.
别让其他孩子打扰你。
Bye bye.
再见。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(horse whinnies)
(马马嘶声)
(cart rattling)
(车震动)
- Monsieur Burnier Go on, ey.
-  [mr Burnier]继续，嘿。
Oh up.
哦。
- Hello.
-  -  -  -  -  - 你好。
- Annette you should be in school by now.
- 安妮特，你现在应该在学校了。
- Grandma said I could stay until you came back.
- 奶奶说我可以 待到你回来。
- Now let's try and get him out of here.
- 现在我们试着把他弄出去。
- Hello.
-  -  -  -  -  - 你好。
- You take his legs Annette.
- 你扶着他的腿，安妮特。
- Oh you poor little thing, what have they done to you?
- 哦，可怜的小东西， 他们对你做了什么？
- I've got to wear these white trousers all of the time.
- 我得穿这些白色的 一直穿裤子。
- Careful, careful.
- 小心，小心。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
Way up, there we go.
往上走，好了。
You alright.
你好的。
- Let's get you in, we'll get you in.
- 我们帮你进去，我们帮你进去。
There you're home again.
你又回家了。
There you are.
你在这儿。
- Monsieur Burnier Mind the door.
- [伯尼尔先生]当心门。
- Grandman Burnier You're back now Dani.
- [伯尼尔爷爷]你回来了，丹尼。
- Where's Klaus?
- 克劳斯在哪儿？
- Oh don't worry, he's around here somewhere.
- 哦，别担心，他 就在这附近。
- Hey over on my bed, on my bed.
- 嘿，到我床上来，到我床上来。
Put him over on my bed.
把他放在我的床上。
- I'll get him for you in a minute.
- 我马上给你叫他来。
- I want him now.
- 我现在就要他。
- Oh, all right I'll go get him.
- 哦，好吧，我去叫他。
- Oh his leg is heavy.
- 哦，他的腿很重。
There we go.
好了。
- I thought he'd have to stay in hospital.
- 我以为他得呆在医院里
- Well they did want him to,
- 他们确实想让他这么做
but he made such a fuss I decided to bring him home.
但他小题大做，我 我决定把他带回家。
- I'm glad you did, it means I can look after him now.
- 我很高兴你这么做，这意味着 我现在可以照顾他了。
- There you are.
- 你在这儿。
(cat meows)
(喵喵叫的猫)
Now, would you like a nice hot drink
现在，你想喝点热饮吗
and a gingerbread biscuit?
还有姜饼饼干？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Come on, I'll get something for you as well.
- 来吧，我去拿 也给你拿点东西。
- If you want anything, just tell me all right?
- 如果你想要什么 告诉我，好吗？
- You know I went right down to the bottom of the cliff.
- 你知道我直接下去了 到悬崖的底部。
- I know, but it wasn't your fault was it?
- 我知道，但那不是你的错，对吧？
Dani you must promise me never to go near
丹妮，你必须答应我永远不要靠近
that Lucien Morell again, do you understand?
吕西安·莫雷尔 再说一遍，你明白吗？
You mustn't even speak to him.
你甚至不能和他说话。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Let me see it.
- 让我看看。
What's the matter?
出什么事了？
I'm not going to eat you.
我不会吃你的。
Come on.
来吧。
Hmm.
嗯。
Do you have any proper tools?
你有合适的工具吗？
Come with me, I'd like to show you something.
跟我来，我想 给你看样东西。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
Have you ever thought of taking up woodcarving?
你有没有想过 学木雕？
Well you should.
嗯，你应该这么做。
You've got talent.
你很有天赋。
It's not everyone who can get a good likeness.
不是每个人 都能拍得很像。
Come here.
到这里来。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
Now watch.
现在的手表。
I'm going to show you what these tools do,
我将向你展示这些工具的作用，
now watch carefully.
现在仔细看。
(tools tapping)
(工具开发)
You see?
你看到了什么?
The little piece out very carefully, and not to go too deep.
这小块很 小心点，不要陷得太深。
The pointy ones tend to dig right into the wood.
尖头的会 直接挖到木头里。
Yeah, have a go.
是啊，试试吧。
Fairly deep to begin with, but not too near the edge.
一开始就相当深， 但又不会太靠近边缘。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
(tools tapping)
(工具开发)
That's right, that's right, that's good.
对，对，很好。
Now let's think what we've got to do.
现在让我们想想我们该做什么。
We've got to clear it's head.
我们得清理它的头。
(talking drowned out by peaceful music)
（谈话被平和的音乐淹没）
(footsteps clicking)
(脚步点击)
- Lucien?
——吕西安?
Well, how was it?
嗯，怎么样？
- All right.
- 好吧。
- Didn't the teacher say anything to you?
- 老师没跟你说什么吗？
- No.
——没有。
- And the other children?
- 其他孩子呢？
- Nothing.
——什么都没有。
- I've been worrying about you all day.
- 我一整天都在担心你。
Perhaps it'll be all right now.
也许现在就好了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(door clatters)
(门哗啦啦地声音)
Come on Marie, the food's out already.
拜托，玛丽，食物已经卖完了。
- Little coward.
- 小懦夫。
- That's enough Marie.
- 够了，玛丽。
- Oh ma, why did you let him do it?
- 天啊，你为什么让他这么做？
You should have made him go to school.
你应该让他去上学的。
- He did go to school, leave the poor boy alone.
- 他确实去上学了 别去烦这个可怜的孩子。
- He did not go to school.
- 他没去上学。
I don't know where he's been all day,
我不知道他这一天去哪了
but it certainly wasn't at school.
但肯定不是在学校。
- Lucien?
- 吕西安？
- I met the school teacher on the way home
- 我在回家的路上遇到了学校老师
and he asked me where Lucien was today,
他问我吕西安今天在哪里
and was everything all right.
一切都好吗？
- Lucien.
——吕西安。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- Teacher When I'm finished with this drawing
- [老师]当我 画完这幅画
I'd like the older ones to copy it down
我想让年纪大的把它抄下来
in their exercise books,
在他们的练习本上，
we'll have more time after the break if you need it.
之后我们会有更多的时间 如果你需要休息的话。
- Do you know what Lucien Morell has done?
- 你知道Lucien Morell做了什么吗？
He dropped Dani's kitten into the ravine
他把达尼的小猫扔进了峡谷
and Dani tried to get it back.
达尼想把它拿回来
He pushed him and Dani fell in and broke his leg.
他推了他和达尼一把 摔倒摔断了腿。
Do you know what Lucien Morell did?
你知道Lucien Morell做了什么吗？
He pushed my brother over the ravine.
他把我弟弟推下了峡谷。
- Teacher And this will be for the younger ones as well.
- [老师]这将是 对年轻的孩子也一样。
I'm going to begin
我要开始了
with some of the ways in which it spreads diseases.
用一些方法进去 从而传播疾病。
It's such an innocent looking little thing.
太天真了 看起来很小的东西。
And yet it can cause so much harm.
然而它却能造成如此大的伤害。
(book slams)
(书砰的一声关上了)
(children laughing)
(孩子们的笑声)
- Teacher Bernard.
- [老师]Bernard。
- Sir?
——先生?
- Bring me that piece of paper.
- 把那张纸给我。
Put it on my desk.
把它放在我桌上。
(children laughing)
(孩子们的笑声)
Is this your writing Annette?
这是你写的吗，安妮特？
- Yes sir.
- 是的，先生。
- Do you really think this is necessary?
- 你真的认为这是必要的吗？
- It's true sir.
- 是真的，先生。
- I know it's true.
- 我知道这是真的。
I said do you really think it's necessary?
我说你真的认为有必要吗？
I find it difficult to understand Lucien's behavior,
我发现很难 理解吕西安的行为
and we're all very glad
我们都很高兴
it didn't turn out any worse than it did.
结果并没有比预想的更糟。
No doubt he'll think twice
毫无疑问，他会三思而后行
before doing any such stupid thing again.
再做这种蠢事之前。
But if I hear any more malicious gossip over this matter
但如果我再听到恶毒的话 关于这件事的流言
I shall be very, very cross.
我会非常非常生气。
(children chattering)
(孩子们聊天)
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
(tools tapping)
(工具开发)
- Yes that's good.
- 是的，很好。
Yes, I like it.
是的，我喜欢。
Oh yeah, you can't have a Noah's Ark without lions.
哦，是的，你不能有 没有狮子的诺亚方舟。
(tools tapping)
(工具开发)
You know you'll soon be able to sell some of your models?
你知道你很快就会的 卖一些你们的模型？
Would you like that?
你喜欢吗？
- Do you really mean that?
- 你是说真的吗？
- Course I do.
- 我当然知道。
There's a man in the village who sells my carvings,
村子里有个男人 他卖我的雕刻品，
we could take some of yours and show them to him.
我们可以取一些 你的给他看看。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
(tools tapping)
(工具开发)
- At school today they announced a handwork competition.
- 今天在学校他们宣布 手工比赛。
- Oh yes?
- 哦，是吗？
What's the prize going to be?
奖品是什么？
- I don't know but that doesn't really matter.
- 我不知道，但是 这不重要。
- Aren't you going to enter?
- 你不去参加吗？
- Yes, I'll show them I'm better than all of them.
- 是的，我会告诉他们我是 比他们所有人都好。
- Oh I'm sure you are.
- 哦，我确定你是。
Was there ever any doubt?
有任何疑问吗？
- I'm going to carve a galloping horse.
- 我要雕刻一匹奔腾的马。
Its mane and its tail, streaming out behind it.
它的鬃毛和尾巴， 在它身后流淌。
- But why try a horse?
- 但为什么要骑马呢？
Why not use your Noah's Ark?
为什么不用你的诺亚方舟？
- It's a present, for a little boy.
- 这是给一个小男孩的礼物。
- Your brother?
- 你哥哥？
- No, he lives near me.
不，他住得离我很近。
He got hurt in an accident.
他在一次事故中受伤了。
- Oh, badly?
- 哦，糟糕吗？
- Broke his leg.
- 摔断了腿。
- Oh dear.
- 哦，天哪。
Aren't you going to tell me about it?
你不打算告诉我吗？
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- He was playing up in the mountains
- 他在山上玩
and a boy came and teased him.
有个男孩过来戏弄他。
Said he would drop his kitten over a ravine
说他会放下他的 小猫越过峡谷
he wasn't really going to, and then it happened.
他并不是真的要去 去，然后就发生了。
And Dani went after it, I couldn't stop--
Dani追着它跑，我停不下来——
- What are you doing?
- 你在做什么？
- You don't want me here now.
- 你现在不想让我在这里。
- Woodcarver Why ever not?
- [木雕师]为什么不呢？
- No-one else does.
- 没人知道。
- What am I going to do for a friend if you go now?
- 我该怎么办呢 如果你现在走，为了朋友？
Come, sit down.
来，坐下。
Come on.
来吧。
That's better.
这是更好的。
How is he now?
他现在怎么样了？
- His sister won't let me go and see him.
- 他姐姐不让我去看他。
- Woodcarver Oh, is she still angry with you?
- [木雕师]哦，是 她还在生你的气？
- She's always telling other people about it.
- 她总是说个不停 别人也会说。
- Hmm, it won't be easy.
- 嗯，这可不容易。
People are slow to forget.
人是慢慢忘记的。
It's a good thing you're doing, stick at it.
还好你 做，坚持下去。
Go on, don't let her discourage you.
继续，别让她打击你。
(horse whinnies)
(马马嘶声)
- Monsieur Burnier There's Annette on the bridge.
-  [mr Burnier]有 Annette在桥上。
- Dani There's Annette.
-  [Dani]那是Annette。
- Monsieur Burnier Hello Annette.
-  [mr Burnier]你好，Annette。
- Hello.
-  -  -  -  -  - 你好。
- I didn't think you were going to get back.
- 我没想到你 我们会回去的。
- Grandma Burnier Hello.
- [奶奶Burnier]你好。
- Now we can all go for a walk together.
- 现在我们可以一起去散步了。
- I'm afraid it's a bit soon for that.
- 恐怕现在说这个有点早了。
- Why?
——为什么?
- Come on Dani.
- 得了吧，丹妮。
- Oh.
——哦。
- Careful.
——小心。
There you are.
你在这儿。
- Mind out.
- 小心点。
Watch me.
看我。
- That's splendid Dani.
- 太棒了，Dani。
That's splendid.
这是辉煌的。
- Look, one of my legs is shorter than the other.
- 看，我的一条腿 比另一个短。
- Oh Dani don't be silly.
- 哦，达尼，别傻了
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
What is it?
是什么？
What's the matter?
出什么事了？
- Go on Dani, show your Granny how you can climb the steps.
- 去吧，达尼，给你奶奶看看 你怎么爬台阶。
- Annette.
——安妮特。
Dani won't ever walk again properly.
达尼再也不能正常走路了。
He'll always have a limp.
他会一直一瘸一拐的。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
Eh up.
嗯。
Come on.
来吧。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- It's a Noah's Ark.
- 这是诺亚方舟。
I made it for Dani.
我是为Dani做的。
- Do you know what you've done?
- 你知道你做了什么吗？
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wood smashes)
(木打碎)
Don't you ever come here again.
别再来这里了。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- Madame Morell What's the matter?
- [莫雷尔夫人]怎么了？
Can't you tell me?
你不能告诉我吗？
Hmm?
嗯?
(saw scraping)
(看到刮)
- I'm sorry.
- 对不起。
That can't have been easy.
那一定不容易。
I hope this doesn't make you want to give up carving.
我希望这不会 你想放弃雕刻。
- It's all right for you.
- 对你来说没关系。
- Maybe, we'll have to see.
- 也许吧，我们得看看。
(saw scraping)
(看到刮)
- Oh, I've got something for you.
- 哦，我有东西给你。
Hi, here it is
嗨，给你
- Oh, thank you.
- 哦，谢谢。
- Hey, have you heard?
嘿，你听说了吗？
- The young Burnier child's going to have a permanent limp.
-  Burnier家的小孩 要永远跛行了。
- No.
——没有。
- Aye.
——啊。
- What a shame.
- 太遗憾了。
- It's not right is it?
- 不对，是吧？
He should be locked up, he should.
他应该被关起来，他应该。
- All right just give him time.
好吧，给他点时间。
- Girl Oh Annette, is this for the competition?
- 哦，安妮特，是 这是为了比赛吗？
- Girl Gosh it's marvelous isn't it?
- [女孩]天哪，太神奇了，不是吗？
- Annette I was making it for Dani anyway.
——[安妮特]我做的 反正是给Dani做的。
- Oh Annette it's bound to win the prize.
- 哦，安妮特，它一定会得奖的。
- No, I think Bernard's going to get the prize.
- 不，我想是伯纳德 要得奖了。
- Oh we've got a dog just like that.
- 哦，我们也有一只这样的狗。
- It's not a dog you idiot, it's a bear.
- 这不是狗，你个白痴，这是熊。
- Girl Oh I'm sorry, I really did think it was a dog.
- [女孩]哦，对不起，我 我真的以为是狗。
- Come on, anyone can see it's a bear.
- 拜托，谁都能看出来是只熊。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
(tools scraping)
(工具刮)
- You're not as stupid as you look are you?
- 你没那么蠢 就像你看起来的那样吗？
- You'll see, when you win the prize
- 你赢了奖就知道了
they'll all want to be your friends.
他们都想成为你的朋友。
Come on, let's eat.
来吧，我们吃饭吧。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wood cracking)
(木材开裂)
- Annette!
——安妮特!
Look what I found in the woodpile.
看我在柴堆里找到了什么。
I found a rhinoceros, a buffalo and a tortoise.
我发现了一头犀牛，一只 水牛和乌龟。
I think the fairies made them, don't you?
我觉得是仙女做的，你觉得呢？
- Don't be so stupid.
- 别犯傻了。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- Mama have you taken my horse?
- 妈妈，你牵走我的马了吗？
- Madam Morell No, Marie have you taken Lucien's horse?
- [莫雷尔夫人]不，玛丽 你把吕西安的马牵走了吗？
- Marie No.
-  [Marie]不。
- Madam Morell Are you sure
- [莫雷尔夫人]你确定吗
you didn't bring it in with you?
你没把它带来吗？
- No.
——没有。
- Marie Could it have blown off the balcony?
-  [Marie]有可能吗 从阳台上被吹走了？
- Oh no.
- 哦，不。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
- Oh Lucien.
- 哦，Lucien。
- Has it broken?
- 坏了吗？
- Madam Morell How could it!
- [莫雷尔夫人]怎么可能！
- Oh, somebody's trodden on it.
- 哦，有人踩过它了。
- Why can't people mind where they're going?
- 为什么人们不介意 他们要去哪里？
Oh.
哦。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
Isn't there anything we can do with it?
我们就没有什么办法了吗？
- Oh hello.
- 哦，你好。
- Hi.
- 嗨。
- Woodcarver How goes the carving?
- [木雕师]雕得怎么样了？
When are you going to win that prize?
你打算什么时候赢得那个奖？
- I'm not going to win that prize.
- 我不会赢得那个奖的。
My horse is all smashed.
我的马都摔坏了。
- Oh no.
- 哦，不。
Oh I am sorry.
哦，我很抱歉。
- It fell over and someone must have trampled on it.
- 它倒下了，有人 一定是被人踩了。
Now I can't enter anything for the competition.
现在我不能输入任何东西了 为了比赛。
- Well, you could enter something else.
- 嗯，你可以输入别的东西。
What about the chamois set you did?
那你做的那套麂皮呢？
That was quite good.
真是太好了。
- I didn't have the proper tools then
- 那时我没有合适的工具
and they'll think I can't do anything better.
他们会认为我 没有比这更好的了。
- Woodcarver Well, does it matter what they think?
- [木雕工]是吗 他们怎么想很重要吗？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Why?
——为什么?
- Because they all hate me and they think I'm no good.
- 因为他们都恨我 他们觉得我不好。
- And you think that winning that prize
- 你认为赢得那个奖
will make them think better of you?
会让他们对你刮目相看吗？
They won't.
他们不会。
- Then what's the point of trying?
- 那尝试的意义是什么？
- Because you have to earn the love and respect of others
- 因为你得挣钱 对他人的爱和尊重
and you'll never do that by doing things for yourself.
你永远也做不到 为自己做事。
But who am I to be talking of winning
但我有什么资格谈论胜利
the love and respect of other people?
别人的爱和尊重？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Come here.
- 过来。
I hope you can keep a secret,
我希望你能保守秘密，
because I'm going to tell you something
因为我要告诉你一些事情
I've never told anyone else.
我从没告诉过别人。
I robbed a bank once.
我抢过一次银行。
Oh it's all right this isn't it, sit down.
哦，没事的，这不是，坐下。
I used to work at the bank once.
我曾经在银行工作过。
I stole the money bit by bit over a long period of time
我一点一点地偷了钱 在很长一段时间里
until they caught me.
直到他们抓住了我。
They put me in prison.
他们把我关进了监狱。
I left my wife, Anna,
我离开了我的妻子安娜
to look after two small children.
照顾两个小孩。
She.
她。
No.
否。
She was a good woman.
她是个好女人。
A godly woman.
一个虔诚的女人。
And it...
和它……
It killed her.
这害死了她。
The humiliation that is.
这是一种耻辱。
She just couldn't take it.
她就是受不了。
My two boys didn't know me when I got out of prison.
我的两个儿子都不认识我 当我出狱的时候
They were fairly well established in their careers.
他们都很好 他们在事业上已经站稳了脚跟。
- Where are they now?
- 他们现在在哪里？
- Geneva.
——日内瓦。
One's in business, one's a doctor.
一个是生意人，一个是医生。
Quite successful I think.
我认为相当成功。
- Don't they ever come here?
- 他们从来没来过这里吗？
- They don't know where I am.
- 他们不知道我在哪里。
When I got out of prison,
当我出狱的时候
I felt if I went to them
我觉得如果我去找他们
it could spoil their chances in their careers.
它会破坏他们的 他们事业上的机会。
So I came here.
于是我来到这里。
I get news of them sometimes
我有时会得到他们的消息
from the man who sells my carvings in the village.
从卖我的 村里的雕刻品。
No.
否。
That's the money I earned from the carvings.
那是我的钱 从雕刻中赚来的。
Almost the same as what I stole.
和我偷的差不多。
There were a lot of people hurt by what I did.
有很多 我的所作所为伤害了很多人。
I don't even know who they were.
我甚至不知道他们是谁。
So I can't repay them,
所以我无法偿还他们，
but I would feel very much better
但是我会感觉好多了
if I could think of something worthwhile to do with it.
如果我能想到什么 值得去做的事。
There, now you know my secret.
好了，现在你知道我的秘密了。
I hope it's safe with you.
我希望它和你在一起很安全。
Good.
好。
And now it's time you were getting off home.
现在是时候了 我们要回家了。
And don't let me hear anymore nonsense of giving in.
别再让我听见了 屈服的无稽之谈。
You may be able to run away from the village,
你也许可以跑 离开村庄，
but you can't run away from yourself.
但你不能逃避自己。
Go on.
继续。
Off you go now and show them what you're made of.
现在你去表演吧 他们知道你是什么做的。
- Teacher I must say that the handwork this year
- [老师]我必须说 这是今年的手工作业
is really quite exceptional.
真的很特别。
I'm sure that all of the parents who are with us today
我敢肯定所有的 今天在场的父母们
must be delighted with this work.
你一定很喜欢这份工作。
- My sister made that.
- 那是我姐姐做的。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
- Dani. - Indeed.
——达尼。 ——事实上。
- I think it's best, don't you?
- 我觉得这是最好的，你觉得呢？
- Well now that you mention it, yes I think I do.
- 既然你提到了 是的，我想我知道。
- You've won the prize Annette, you've won the prize!
- 你得奖了 安妮特，你得奖了！
- Teacher Well having had that decision
- [老师]嗯，既然已经做出了这个决定
taken out of my hands, we come to the boy's entries.
从我手中夺走，我们 来看看男孩的参赛作品。
Yet again the quality is so good, but I have to confess
质量也是如此 不错，但我得承认
there is one that stands out above them all.
有一个站着 在他们之上。
The prize this year for the best boy
这是今年的最佳男孩奖
really must go to Bernard Pile.
我真得去看看Bernard Pile。
(clapping)
(鼓掌)
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
(cat meows)
(喵喵叫的猫)
- What are you playing?
- 你在玩什么？
- Go away!
- 走开！
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
I'm playing with my fairy animals.
我在和我的精灵动物玩。
But Annette said I'm not to talk to you.
但安妮特不让我跟你说话。
- I won't hurt you.
我不会伤害你的。
And I was very sorry about your leg.
对你的腿我也很抱歉。
That's why I made the animals for you.
所以我才给你做了这些动物。
- You didn't make them, I found them behind the woodpile.
- 不是你做的，我 在柴堆后面找到的。
- Annette Dani, supper's ready.
- [安妮特]丹妮，晚饭准备好了。
Dani!
丹尼!
- Coming!
——来了!
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
Come Klaus.
克劳斯。
- Come on, hurry up.
- 快点，快点。
- It's getting cold.
- 天越来越冷了。
- Annette.
——安妮特。
Lucien said he made my fairy animals, but he didn't did he?
Lucien说他造了我的仙女 动物，但他没有，不是吗？
- Dani I've told you not to talk to Lucien.
-  Dani，我告诉过你 不要和吕西安说话。
He'll only hurt you again.
他只会再次伤害你。
- Oh Annette that's not kind.
- 哦，安妮特，这可不好。
- But I only talked to him a teeny weeny bit,
- 但我只跟 只跟他说了一点点
anyway he didn't make them did he?
不管怎么说，他没有做出来，不是吗？
- You found them in the woodpile didn't you?
- 你在 是在柴堆里找到的吧？
So how could he have done?
那么他是怎么做到的呢？
Don't be so silly.
别犯傻了。
- Well he said he did.
- 他说他知道。
But I think the fairies made them, don't you?
但我觉得仙女们 是你造的吧？
- Oh do be quiet Dani, and eat up your soup.
- 哦，安静点Dani， 把汤喝完。
- Annette.
- 安妮特。
- Where's Annette going?
- 安妮特要去哪里？
- I think her conscience is troubling her.
- 我想她良心不安。
- What's that?
- 什么事？
- It's a little thing inside us
- 它是我们内心的一个小东西
that keeps getting in the way.
这总是碍事。
- Oh.
——哦。
- Am I to understand those little animals
- 我能理解那些小动物吗
really were from Lucien?
真的来自吕西安吗？
Oh Annette I don't know what's going on between you two,
哦，安妮特，我不知道是什么 你们俩之间发生了什么
but do you really think it's worth it?
但你真的觉得值得吗？
Don't you see what it's doing to you my dear?
你看不出这是什么吗 对你做了什么，亲爱的？
You've cut of Lucien and God
你剪掉了吕西安和上帝
and now you're beginning to hurt little Dani as well.
现在你开始明白了 也伤害了小达尼。
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
Think about it my dear, think very hard.
好好想想，亲爱的，好好想想。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wind howling)
(风咆哮)
(screams)
(尖叫)
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
(panting)
(喘气)
Monsieur Belldo!
Belldo先生!
(door knocking)
(门敲门)
Monsieur Belldo.
Belldo先生。
(door rattling)
(门咔嗒咔嗒声)
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
Dear Lord.
亲爱的主啊。
Dear Lord Jesus.
亲爱的主耶稣。
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
Why won't you let me in?
你为什么不让我进去？
(melancholy music)
(忧郁的音乐)
Please Lord, please help me.
上帝啊，请帮帮我吧。
Please, please help me.
求求你，求求你帮帮我。
Please, please.
请,请。
(ski's scraping)
(滑雪的刮)
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
Help!
的帮助!
Over here!
在这里!
I've hurt myself.
我弄伤了自己。
I can't get out of here.
我出不去了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
Oh no.
哦,不。
- Can't you walk at all?
- 你一点都不会走吗？
(groans)
(叹息)
Look, if you wait here
听着，如果你在这里等
it'd be best if I go home, get the sledge for you.
我最好还是回家吧 把雪橇给你拿来。
Don't worry, I'll be as quick as I can.
别担心，我会尽快的。
- Won't you be cold?
- 你不会冷吗？
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
- Lucien I won't be long.
-  [Lucien]我不会待太久的。
- Annette Voiceover Oh why did it have to be him?
- [安妮特画外音]哦 为什么一定是他？
Why?
为什么?
Lord Jesus.
主耶稣。
- Dear Lord Jesus,
- 亲爱的主耶稣，
thank you for sending Lucien to help me.
谢谢你派吕西安来帮我。
I'm sorry I've been shutting you out all these months
对不起，我一直在关门 你这几个月都不在
'cause I wanted to hate him, I wanted to punish him.
因为我想去恨 我想惩罚他
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉。
I really am.
真的。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wood cracking)
(木材开裂)
- Annette Voiceover I can't, please don't make me.
- [安妮特画外音]我 不行，请不要逼我。
Please, no.
请,不。
No no, please.
不不，求你了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Do I have to tell him?
- 我一定要告诉他吗？
- Come on.
- 来吧。
- No, wait.
- 不，等等。
I want to tell you something before we go home.
我想告诉你 在我们回家之前。
You know that time your horse fell off the balcony?
你知道那个时候你的 马从阳台上摔下来？
Well it was me.
嗯，是我。
I did it on purpose
我是故意的
because I didn't want you to win the prize.
因为我不想 你赢得了这个奖。
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉。
- Come on.
- 来吧。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
(footsteps clicking)
(脚步点击)
- Annette.
——安妮特。
Oh my dear what has happened to you?
哦，亲爱的，你发生了什么事？
Your father has just this minute gone out looking for you.
你父亲就有这个 我出去找你了。
- Yes, he's seen us.
- 是的他看到我们了
He's just getting some bandages.
他只是在包扎。
- Lucien, come in.
-  Lucien，请进。
You're very welcome.
不客气。
Come.
来了。
Sit down both of you.
你们俩都坐下。
I'll go and get you some good hot soup.
我去给你拿些热汤来。
Annette, I've tried not to interfere
安妮特，我已经尽量不干涉了
but isn't it time you forgave Lucien?
但你是不是该原谅吕西安了？
- I have.
- 我有。
- And have you told him?
- 你告诉他了吗？
- Yes, today in the mountains.
- 是的，今天在山上。
- And what brought this about?
- 这是怎么回事？
- Come on you, lets have you on the sofa.
- 来吧，让你到沙发上来。
Gently, there we are.
轻轻地，我们到了。
Alright, let's have a look at it.
好吧，让我们看一看。
(groaning)
(呻吟)
Where Annette?
安妮特哪里?
- Ow!
——噢!
- Monsieur Burnier Is it here?
-  [mr Burnier]在这里吗？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Well, I just wanted to get out
- 我只是想出去走走
and think about what was said at church last night.
想想是什么 昨晚在教堂说的话。
You know, about the innkeeper not letting Mary and Joesph in
你知道的，关于旅店老板的事 不让玛丽和约瑟夫进来
and people who still don't let Jesus in.
还有那些仍然不让耶稣进入的人
And, ow!
,噢!
Ow.
噢。
Then I fell up by the Belldo's house
然后我在贝尔多家的房子旁边跌倒了
and there was nobody there,
那里一个人也没有
but I still felt like they weren't letting me in on purpose.
但我还是觉得他们 他们不是故意让我进去的
I thought God must feel a bit like that really.
我想上帝一定有感觉 真的有点像。
It was awful.
太可怕了。
And then Lucien arrived of all people
然后吕西安在所有人中出现了
and I just couldn't stand it anymore.
我再也无法忍受了
And so, I had to tell him.
所以，我不得不告诉他。
- Tell him what?
- 告诉他什么？
- It's a secret.
- 这是个秘密。
- Oh.
——哦。
- I'll tell you one day.
- 总有一天我会告诉你的。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
- Come in, come in.
- 进来，进来。
Now, what can I do for you?
现在，我能为你做些什么？
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
- Lucien made them.
- 吕西安做的。
- These are really exceptionally good.
- 这些真的特别好吃。
They're beautiful.
他们是美丽的。
I had no idea that Lucien.
我不知道吕西安。
Why did he not enter for the competition?
他为什么不参加比赛呢？
- He did.
- 是的。
That's what I've come to tell you about.
这就是我来告诉你的事情。
He made a little wooden horse,
他做了一个小木马，
but I broke it because I was so angry about Dani.
但我把它弄坏了，因为我 因为丹妮的事我很生气
But I'm sorry now and I wondered if he could have a prize
但我现在很抱歉，我想知道 如果他能得奖
now that you know about it.
现在你知道了。
- But I haven't got another prize, there were only two.
- 但是我没有另一个 奖品，只有两个。
One was given to Bernard and the other to you.
一个给了伯纳德 另一个给了你。
- Well than he ought to have Bernard's prize,
- 比他应该做的好 得到了伯纳德的奖品
his were much better.
他的好多了。
- Oh no, we couldn't do that.
- 哦，不，我们不能那样做。
After all, Bernard won quite fairly.
毕竟，伯纳德赢得相当公平。
We couldn't take his prize away.
我们不能拿走他的奖品。
If you really want Lucien to have a prize
如果你真的想给吕西安一个奖品
then I think you should give him yours.
那我觉得你应该把你的给他。
After all it was your fault wasn't it?
毕竟这是你的错，不是吗？
Hmm?
嗯?
It seems we have a late entry for the handwork competition.
看来我们有一个迟到的人 为了手工艺比赛。
Indeed, I must say I was as surprised as you are.
的确，我得说我是 和你一样惊讶。
Normally I would not consider such a late entry.
通常我不会 这么晚才入职。
However, during the holidays
然而，在假期里
I came across such a good piece of woodcarving
我遇到过这样一个 很好的木雕
that I've decided to award another prize for it.
我决定授予 另一个奖项
Lucien, would you like to come up and receive it?
吕西安，你想不想 上来领奖吧？
- Thank you.
- 谢谢。
- Well done, you deserve it.
- 干得好，你应得的。
- Annette it's like yours.
- 安妮特，就像你的。
- Is it?
- 是吗？
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
I think you ought to keep it, it's your book.
我想你应该这么做 留着吧，这是你的书。
- No, it's yours now.
- 不，现在是你的了。
The teacher said so.
老师是这么说的。
You've got to keep it.
你得留着它。
- Well I tell you what,
- 我告诉你吧
why don't I have it this month and you have it the next?
为什么这个月没有呢 下个月给你？
- And we'll change every month, all right.
- 我们每个月换一次，好吗？
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
Dani, what are you doing here?
Dani，你在这里做什么？
- Granny said I could come here,
- 奶奶说我可以来这里
'cause dinner's ready and I've had mine.
因为晚餐准备好了，我已经吃过了。
- You shouldn't have come so far.
- 你不应该来这么远。
- I thought you'd be back sooner.
- 我以为你会早点回来。
- Come on.
- 来吧。
- Oh, my leg hurts.
- 哦，我的腿疼。
- Shall I carry him?
- 我来背他好吗？
- Would you like that?
- 你喜欢吗？
- Woo hoo!
- 哇呼！
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
- What are you thinking?
- 你在想什么？
- Dani.
——达尼。
- Don't you think it's time you put all that behind you?
- 你不觉得是时候了吗 你把这些都抛在脑后了？
- It was going so well, and then.
- 一切都很顺利，然后。
Isn't there anything we can do for him?
我们就不能为他做点什么吗？
- No, I don't think we can.
- 不，我想我们做不到。
- Marie Oh, I thought I'd never make it.
-  [Marie]哦，我还以为我做不到呢
- Come on, you must be frozen.
- 拜托，你一定是冻僵了。
What's this?
这是什么?
- Money I think.
- 钱，我想。
- What's it for?
- 这是干什么用的？
- Got it as a tip.
- 这是给你的小费。
- Really?
——真的吗?
- Monsieur Givert, he's a doctor from down by the lake.
- 吉弗特先生，他是个 他是湖边的医生。
Quite famous I believe.
我相信相当有名。
- Isn't that nice of him?
- 他不是很好吗？
- Madam was telling me he's got a clinic.
- 夫人告诉我他开了一家诊所。
People come from all over the world,
人们来自世界各地，
he's some sort of bone specialist
他是个骨骼专家
Honestly he was ever so nice.
老实说，他真是太好了。
- Can he mend broken legs?
- 他会补断腿吗？
- I would think so, yes.
- 我想是的。
Oh, Lucien, you're not still thinking about Dani are you?
哦，吕西安，你不安静 你在想达尼，是吗？
- Could he do it?
- 他能做到吗？
- I suppose so but have no idea how much it would cost?
- 我想是的，但是没有 你知道要花多少钱吗？
- No.
——没有。
- Nor have I.
- 我也没有。
But it'll be far more than the Burniers could afford.
但这远不止 伯尼一家负担不起。
- Forget about Dani, Lucien.
- 别管达妮了，吕西安。
It's over with.
结束了。
- But would he just come and have a look at Dani?
- 但他会来吗 去看看达妮
- What good will that do?
- 那有什么用？
- I just thought that we could find out
- 我只是觉得我们可以找到答案
if anything could be done.
如果还有什么办法的话。
- He leaves tomorrow early.
- 他明天早走。
- We could go now.
- 我们现在可以走了。
- Marie How?
-  [Marie]怎么做？
- On the train.
- 在火车上。
- It's too late.
- 太晚了。
- Not if we hurry.
- 如果我们快点就不会了。
- Lucien don't be silly.
-  Lucien别傻了。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
(wind howling)
(风咆哮)
- Who's that?
- 那是谁？
My boy what brings you here in this weather?
我的孩子，什么风把你吹来了 这种天气来这儿？
(coughing)
(咳嗽)
Are you all right?
你还好吗？
- You know you once said you were saving your money
- 你曾经说过 你在存钱
to give to something worthwhile.
给予有价值的东西。
- Yes.
——是的。
- Well, I think I've found someone who really needs it.
- 我想我找到了 一个真正需要它的人。
If you will give me your money,
如果你愿意把钱给我，
I think little Dani Burnier's leg might be made better.
我想是小Dani Burnier的 腿可能会做得更好。
- How could that be?
- 这怎么可能？
- There's a doctor at the hotel where my sister works
- 有个医生在 我姐姐工作的旅馆
who can mend broken bones.
谁能修补骨折。
My sister said he'd want a lot of money.
我姐姐说他想要很多钱。
I'm going over the pass now
我现在要翻过山口
to ask him to come and have a look at Dani.
请他过来 看看达尼。
- You're going over the pass, in this weather?
- 你要越过 在这种天气下通过？
My boy you must be mad.
我的孩子，你一定是疯了。
You couldn't cross the pass in this weather.
你不能穿过 在这种天气下过关。
- I think I could on my skis,
- 我想我可以用我的滑雪板
the fresh snow won't be too deep yet if I hurry.
新下的雪不会 如果我快点，雪还不会太深。
But it's no good going unless I've got the money.
但这并不好 除非我拿到钱。
- I would give the money if I was sure of the man,
- 我会给钱的 如果我对这个人有把握
but what do we know of him?
但我们对他了解多少呢？
Suppose he should cheat us.
假如他欺骗了我们。
- My sister said he's a very famous man.
- 我姐姐说他是个很有名的人。
Monsieur Givert I think.
我想是吉弗特先生吧。
- Monsieur Givert?
- 吉弗特先生？
Do you know anymore about him?
你还了解他吗？
- He's got a clinic down by the lake
- 他在湖边开了一家诊所
people come to him from all over the world.
人们从 来自世界各地。
- Take it all and give it to Monsieur Givert
- 接受并给予 给吉弗特先生
and tell him it is the payment of a debt.
告诉他这是还债。
- Thank you very much.
- 非常感谢。
- Now you won't forget the message will you?
- 现在你不会忘记了 留言是吗？
- No, I'll say it's a payment of a debt.
- 不，我会说这是偿还债务。
- And don't tell him about me.
- 别把我的事告诉他。
- No?
——不是吗?
- Nor my name.
- 也不是我的名字。
- No, I don't know your name.
- 不，我不知道你的名字。
- Nor where I live.
- 也不是我住的地方。
- No I'll just say it's a payment of a debt.
- 不，我就说是 是对债务的偿还。
Bye bye.
再见。
- Goodbye and be careful, be careful.
- 再见，小心，小心。
(ski's scraping)
(滑雪的刮)
(wind howling)
(风咆哮)
(humming)
(哼)
(bird caws)
(鸟caws)
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Our father who art in heaven,
- 我们在天上的父，
hallowed be thy name, thy kingdom,
愿人都尊你的名，尊你的国，
thy kingdom come, thy will be done.
愿你的国降临，愿你的旨意成就。
(wind howling)
(风咆哮)
I can't feel my feet.
我的脚没知觉了。
Oh it's so cold.
哦，太冷了。
(groaning)
(呻吟)
(sobbing)
(哭泣)
God, help me.
上帝啊，救救我吧。
I'll never get there without a lantern.
没有灯笼我永远也到不了那里。
Are you there God?
上帝，你在吗？
Are you there?
你在吗？
Do you care about me?
你在乎我吗？
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
Oh, God.
哦,上帝。
You helped Annette, when she was stuck in the snow.
你帮了安妮特，当 她被困在雪里了。
Help me, please.
请帮帮我。
Please.
请。
I didn't do that to Dani on purpose.
我不是故意那样对Dani的。
I promise I didn't.
我保证我没有。
Please help me.
请帮帮我。
Please help me to get to the doctor.
请帮我去看医生。
Please.
请。
Please someone come and find me.
请有人来找我吧。
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
(door knocking)
(门敲门)
- Yes?
——是吗?
- Excuse me Monsieur Givert,
- 打扰一下，吉弗特先生，
where you by any chance expecting any, any visitors?
你在哪里 会有人来吗？
- A visitor, at this hour?
- 这时候来了客人？
- Yes, it's like this Monsieur.
- 是的，就像这样，先生。
About quarter of an hour ago,
大约一刻钟前，
I heard a little rap on the door
我听到轻轻的敲门声
and when I went to answer it,
当我去接电话时
there standing on the step is this boy in skis.
站在 台阶上站着一个穿着滑雪板的男孩。
About 12 years old, white as a sheet,
大约12岁，白得像一张纸，
looking more like a ghost than a boy.
看起来更像个鬼，而不像个孩子。
(laughs)
(笑)
"I want to see Monsieur Givert" says he.
“我想见吉弗特先生，”他说。
Without so much as a good morning.
连一句早安都没有。
Then he falls down on his knees
然后他跪倒在地
and leans his head against the door post.
把头靠在门柱上。
"Well" says I, "you can't come calling on people
“嗯，”我说，“你不能 去拜访别人吧
"at this time in the morning, he's sound asleep in his bed."
“在早晨的这个时候， 他在床上睡得很熟。”
"Then I'll wait" says he.
“那我就等着吧。”他说。
And he sinks his head down in his knees.
他把头埋在膝盖里。
Well sir, I don't like to see a child like that.
先生，我不喜欢 看到一个孩子那样。
So I takes his skis off, and I drags him inside
所以我把他的滑雪板取下来， 然后把他拖进去
and I puts him on a chair.
我把他放在椅子上。
"Where have you come from?" says I.
“你从哪里来？”我问。
"From Pays-d'Enhaut" says he.
“从佩斯- 德恩豪来的，”他说。
"Hows that?" says I, "the early train's not in yet."
“怎么了？”我说，“那个。 早班火车还没到呢。”
"I came through the pass" says he.
“我是从关口来的”他说。
Yes Monsieur, through the pass.
是的，先生，通过通行证。
And the more I look at him,
我越看他，
the more likely I feel to believe it.
我就越有可能相信它。
And when I saw your light on
当我看到你的灯亮着
I thought I'd come and see if you'd like to see him too.
我想我应该过来看看 如果你也想看看他的话。
- Well, I'll come and see him certainly.
- 好吧，我一定去看他。
But as for coming through the pass
但至于通过关口
I don't believe a word of it.
我一个字也不相信。
It must have been terrible out there last night.
那一定很可怕 昨晚在外面。
- Well you'll see for yourself sir.
- 你会亲眼看到的，先生。
- Oh dear.
- 哦，天哪。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
I'll take him to my room.
我带他去我的房间。
Bring me a hot water bottle and some brandy.
给我来杯热水 一瓶和一些白兰地。
Oh and some hot coffee.
哦，再来点热咖啡。
- Yes sir.
- 是的，先生。
- And be as quick as you can.
- 而且越快越好
- At once sir.
- 马上，先生。
- Ah right.
- 好吧。
- Monsieur.
——先生。
- Ah.
——啊。
- A hot water bottle.
- 一个热水瓶。
- Thank you Porter.
- 谢谢你波特。
- And uh, Brandy Monsieur.
- 还有白兰地，先生。
- Thank you.
- 谢谢。
- Oh, the poor boy.
- 哦，可怜的孩子。
Yes.
是。
- Thank you.
- 谢谢。
- I'll get the coffee Monsieur.
- 我去拿咖啡，先生。
- That's right.
- 没错。
(suspenseful music)
(悬疑的背景音乐)
- Who are you?
- 你是谁？
- I'm Monsieur Givert, I understand you wanted to see me.
- 我是吉弗特先生，我 我知道你想见我。
- Are you the great, clever, famous doctor?
- 你是伟大的吗？ 聪明，有名的医生？
- (laughs) No, I'm just a doctor.
- （笑）不，我只是个医生。
- Can you make lame children walk?
- 你能让跛脚的孩子走路吗？
- It depends why they're lame, sometimes I can.
- 这要看他们为什么 很差劲，有时候我可以。
- He fell off a precipice
- 他从悬崖上摔了下来
and now he has to walk with crutches.
现在他得拄着拐杖走路。
- Who?
——谁?
- Little Dani Burnier.
- 小Dani Burnier。
He lives in the chalet next to ours.
他住在我们隔壁的小木屋里。
I was going to ask whether you could make him well again.
我正要问你是否 你能不能让他好起来。
- Coffee Monsieur.
- 咖啡先生。
- Thank you Porter.
- 谢谢你波特。
- Here we are.
- 我们到了。
- There we are.
- 好了。
Here hmm.
嗯。
How did you hear of me?
你是怎么知道我的？
- My sister's a maid here, she told me.
- 我妹妹是这里的女佣，她告诉我的。
- But how did you get here in that storm?
- 但是你是怎么在暴风雨中来到这里的？
- I came over the pass on my skis.
- 我是用我的滑雪板翻过山口的。
- (laughs) You couldn't have done, not that night.
- （笑）你不能 做了，那天晚上不行。
- But I did.
- 但我做到了。
Please sir, would this be enough to make Dani better?
先生，请问这是 足以让达尼好起来吗
(bell ringing)
(铃响)
- Excuse me, sir.
- 对不起，先生。
- What's your name?
- 你叫什么名字？
- Lucien Morell.
-  Lucien Morell。
- Lucien, bfore we go any further
- 吕西安，在我们继续之前
I must know where this money came from.
我必须知道这些钱是从哪里来的。
Do you know how much there is here?
你知道这里有多少钱吗？
- No, but my sister said you'd want a lot.
- 不，但我姐姐说你想要很多。
Isn't it enough?
这还不够吗？
- (laughs) That depends whether
- （笑）那要看
you want to buy my clinic as well.
你还想买下我的诊所。
Lucien, where did you get it?
吕西安，你从哪儿弄来的？
- An old man I know, I'm friends with him.
- 一个我认识的老人，我和他是朋友。
And there's a message with it he said.
他说，里面有一条信息。
It was a payment of a debt and you are to take it all.
这是一笔债务的偿还 你要全部拿走。
- Who is this old man?
- 这位老人是谁？
What's his name?
他叫什么名字？
- I don't know.
- 我不知道。
- Where does he live?
- 他住在哪里？
- Please, he made me promise not to tell you.
- 拜托，是他逼我的 我保证不告诉你。
He's sort of a secret and no one goes to see him except me.
他是个秘密，没有 只有我一个人去见他。
- All right, I shan't ask anything more for now.
- 好吧，我不问了 现在还需要什么吗？
But tell me about little Dani's accident.
跟我说说小达尼的事故吧。
How did it happen and when?
这是怎么发生的，什么时候发生的？
- It was my fault really.
- 真的是我的错。
I was teasing him and then,
我在逗他，然后
I pretended to drop to drop his cat over a ravine.
我假装喝醉了 把他的猫扔到峡谷里。
And then by mistake, I really did.
然后不小心，我真的这么做了。
Dani went after it, fell and broke his leg.
丹妮去追它， 摔断了腿。
And ever since, he's never walked properly again.
从那以后，他再也没有 又能正常走路了。
And I thought perhaps--
我想也许——
- All right.
- 好吧。
We'll go and see Dani together.
我们一起去看Dani。
It may be that God is going to make you
也许是上帝要创造你
the means of curing him.
治疗他的方法。
You know, you have a lot to thank God for.
你知道吗，你有很多事情要感谢上帝。
I think he must have been looking after you
我想他一定有 一直在照顾你
in a very special way last night,
昨晚以一种非常特别的方式
or you would never have got over that pass alone.
否则你永远不会 一个人过了那个关。
Now, I think you'd better get some sleep.
现在，我想你最好睡一会儿。
(door knocking)
(门敲门)
Before I take you home, hm?
在我带你回家之前，嗯？
- Porter Monsieur Givert, ah, Monsieur Givert!
——吉弗特先生， 啊，吉弗特先生！
- Oh sir, Porter tells me you've got my little brother.
- 哦，先生，波特告诉我了 你抓了我弟弟。
Is he all right?
他还好吗？
- Yes, exhausted but all right.
- 是的，很累，但还好。
- Oh sir, we've been searching for him all night.
- 哦，先生，我们去过 整晚都在找他。
- Don't worry my dear, I think he'll be all right now.
- 别担心，亲爱的，我 我想他现在会没事的。
Perhaps you'd tell Dani's parents
也许你该告诉丹妮的父母
that I'll be along to see him, would you?
我会去看他的，你会吗？
- Yes, thank you Monsieur.
- 好的，谢谢你，先生。
- Thank you so much, you're very helpful, thank you.
- 太谢谢你了，你真是 很有帮助，谢谢。
- Porter I'll certain the management
- [搬运工]我会向管理部门确认的
will give you the day off.
给你放一天假。
- Dr. Givert I'm sure they will.
-  [Dr. Givert]我肯定他们会的。
(bell ringing)
(铃响)
(cheerful music)
(欢快的音乐)
(coughs)
(咳嗽)
- Dani, would you like a sweet?
-  Dani，你想来点甜食吗？
- Yes, go on.
- 是的，继续。
- (laughs) Does your leg hurt you?
- （笑）你的腿疼吗？
- No.
——没有。
- Hmm.
——嗯。
- No Monsieur.
- 不，先生。
- Monsieur.
——先生。
Only sometimes when I walk without my crutches.
只是有时候当我 不用拐杖走路。
Would you like to see my crutches?
你想看看我的拐杖吗？
- Very much indeed.
- 非常喜欢。
- Ah, (laughs) wonderful.
- 啊，（笑）太棒了。
Just like a kangaroo.
就像袋鼠一样。
Now give me your crutches
把你的拐杖给我
and let me see you walk without them, hm?
让我看看你不戴眼镜走路，好吗？
(peaceful music)
(和平的音乐)
Ah (laughs).
啊(笑)。
- Lets have some coffee, shall we Annette?
- 我们喝点咖啡吧，安妮特？
- Yes Grandma.
- 是的，奶奶。
- There we go
- 好了
Now.
现在。
Hmm, now.
嗯,现在。
Hmm-mm.
哼唱旋律。
Yeah, yes.
是的,是的。
- Well?
——好吗?
- Would you like to be able to run around
- 你想要能够到处跑吗
like other little boys, hmm?
像其他小男孩一样，嗯？
- Hmm-mm.
——哼唱旋律。
- Dani, where's that fine cat gone?
-  Dani，那只漂亮的猫去哪了？
- To the woodshed, would you like to see him?
- 去柴棚，我会 你想见他吗？
- Yes please.
- 好的，谢谢。
Whey.
乳清。
I think I may be able to help you,
我想我也许能帮到你，
though I'd have to see the X-Rays first.
不过我得先看x光片。
I think the bone was not properly set
我觉得骨头没有固定好
and has joined up in the wrong way.
并以错误的方式加入。
I could break it again and pull it out straight,
我可以再把它弄坏 把它拔出来，
but it would mean an operation and a long stay in hospital.
但这意味着要动手术 还要在医院呆很长时间。
Would you be willing to let him come?
你愿意让他来吗？
- Well, um, how much would it cost?
- 嗯，那要花多少钱？
- It wouldn't cost you anything, Lucien has paid.
- 不会花你钱的 吕西安已经付过钱了。
But I can't explain that now,
但我现在无法解释，
we must decide before Dani comes back.
我们必须在达尼回来之前做出决定。
Will you let me take him?
你能让我带他去吗？
- Yes.
——是的。
- When?
——什么时候?
- Tomorrow, I'll be leaving on the early train,
- 明天，我会 坐早班火车离开，
I'll take Dani with me.
我带达尼一起去。
- On the train?
- 在火车上？
Where am I going?
我要去哪里？
Where Annette?
安妮特哪里?
- Dani, you're coming with me down to the lake,
- 达尼，你来了 和我一起去湖边
where I'm going to make your leg better.
我要让你的腿好起来
- And Annette, and Klaus, and Grandma and Papa.
- 还有安妮特还有克劳斯 还有爷爷奶奶。
- Oh, Dani we can't all come.
- 达尼，我们不能都来。
- Does the girl know anything about looking after children?
- 那女孩知道什么吗 如何照顾孩子？
- She brought this one up.
- 是她提出来的
- And Annette.
- 还有安妮特。
So, I want to see you two at the station
那么，我想在车站见到你们两个
at half past eight tomorrow morning and enough things
明天八点半 早上和足够的东西
to last you for two or three months, all right?
陪你两个或 三个月，好吗？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Now, I must take poor Lucien home.
- 现在，我得带可怜的吕西安回家了。
And then I have another small matter to deal with.
然后是另一个 小事要处理。
(bells ringing)
(钟声)
Who's that old man?
那个老人是谁？
Oi, stop.
Oi,停下来。
Do you know him?
你认识他吗？
The money.
这笔钱。
Excuse me, Monsieur!
对不起，先生！
Monsieur!
先生！
Excuse me, Monsieur.
打扰一下，先生。
Excuse me, Monsieur, I know this sounds rather silly
对不起，先生，我知道 这听起来很傻
but this sock, do you know anything about this sock?
但是这只袜子，你知道吗 这只袜子怎么样？
- No, no no, no.
- 不，不，不。
- And that little boy down there?
- 下面那个小男孩呢？
- No, no, no.
- 不不不。
- Please Monsieur.
- 拜托，先生。
No it can't be.
不，不可能。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
Come with me.
跟我来。
Oh where have you been?
哦，你去哪儿了？
- Oh, such a long time.
- 哦，这么长时间了。
- What have you been doing?
- 你最近在做什么？
Why didn't you get in touch with me?
你为什么不联系我？
- I've been so ashamed.
- 我太羞愧了。
- But you might have known,
- 但你可能早就知道
we've been wondering where you were.
我们一直在想你去哪儿了。
- Woodcarver It would have spoiled your life.
- [木雕匠]会的 会毁了你的生活。
- Dr. Givert But why did you go away?
- [吉弗特博士]但你为什么要离开？
- Woodcarver It would have spoiled all your chances.
- [木雕匠]会的 毁了你所有的机会。
- Dr. Givert Oh no, no.
- [吉弗特博士]哦，不，不。
- It would have.
- 会的。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
Oh it's so good to see you my boy.
哦，见到你真是太好了，我的孩子。
So good.
很好。
- Lucien, I would like you to meet my father.
-  Lucien，我想 让你见见我父亲。
He's coming home with me as well.
他也要和我一起回家。
(laughing)
(笑着说)
Come on father, get on the sleigh.
来吧，爸爸，坐上雪橇。
There we are, what a day.
好了，这是多么美好的一天啊。
(laughs) Lets go, away.
（笑）走吧，走吧。
(cheerful music)
(欢快的音乐)
- Hello Lucien, where are you going?
- 你好，Lucien，你要去哪里？
- I'm going to the station,
- 我要去车站，
Annette and Dani are coming today.
Annette和Dani今天要来。
- Oh, give them my love.
- 哦，代我向他们问好。
- All right.
- 好吧。
- Hello Lucien.
- 你好，Lucien。
- Good morning.
- 早上好。
- Grandma Burnier Do you think they will have changed?
- [伯尼尔奶奶]你 觉得他们会变吗？
- Monsieur Burnier Oh mother, surely not in three months.
- [伯尼尔先生]哦，妈妈， 肯定不会在三个月内。
- Grandma Burnier My dear when you were their age.
- [伯尼尔奶奶]亲爱的 你在他们这个年纪的时候。
- Monsieur Burnier Yes I know.
- [伯尼尔先生]是的，我知道。
And they were dragged off to the city
他们被拖到城里去了
by some stranger as well.
还有一些陌生人。
- The place has been so quiet without them.
- 这个地方已经 没有他们，这里很安静。
- Yes, it has rather.
- 是的，确实如此。
(train horn whistles)
（火车汽笛声）
(train rattling)
(火车咔嗒咔嗒声)
Can you see them yet?
你看到了吗？
- Lucien Voiceover It was your fault.
- [吕西安画外音]是你的错。
it was all your fault.
都是你的错。
- There they are.
- 他们来了。
Look, can you see them?
看，你能看见他们吗？
- Yes.
——是的。
- Annette Voiceover It was your fault.
- [安妮特画外音]是你的错。
It was all your fault.
都是你的错。
- Hello.
-  -  -  -  -  - 你好。
Come on, come here.
来吧，过来。
- Dr. Givert Voiceover Maybe that God
-  [Dr. Givert画外音]也许是那个上帝
is going to make you means of curing him.
会使你成为医治他的手段。
- Lucien, watch me.
-  Lucien，看着我。
(cheerful music)
(欢快的音乐)
- Grandma Burnier Be careful.
- [奶奶Burnier]小心点。
Come on let me help you.
来吧，让我来帮你。
(cheerful music)
(欢快的音乐)